Ajit Jain

ABOUT

Computer Science Ph.D. with 15+ years of experience in conceptualizing, developing, and evaluating state-of-the-art solutions, connecting ideas from human-computer interaction, artificial intelligence, information retrieval, information visualization, and software engineering.

5+ years of experience in managing people, helping them grow and realize their potential. Both as an individual contributor and manager, I have helped create a culture of excellence in the teams I have been a part of, helping them deliver unprecedented value to stakeholders.

EDUCATION

Texas A&M University

College Station, USA

Ph.D. in Computer Science

2015-2021

Co-Advisors: Dr. Andruid Kerne and Dr. Ruihong Huang

Thesis: How to Support Situated Design Education through AI-Based Analytics

Texas A&M University

College Station, USA

M.S. in Computer Science

2011-2014

Advisor: Dr. Andruid Kerne

Thesis: TweetBubble: A Twitter Extension Stimulates Exploratory Browsing

Delhi Technological University

Delhi, India

B.E. in Information Technology

2003-2007

Industry Experience

Full-Time

Audigent
Research and Engineering, Data Analytics

New York, USA Mar 2022–Present

- → Help drive executive strategy by contributing state-of-the-art solutions, conceptualizing and developing them in collaboration with stakeholders across business units.
- → Design, develop, and optimize large-scale data systems focused on deriving audience analytics and presenting them via dashboards.
- → Research, prototype, and recommend new techniques, including AI/ML approaches, for advancing derivation and optimization of audience segments.
- → Mentor junior engineers in designing and implementing automation, optimization, and analysis processes.

Amobee
Research and Engineering, Data Analytics

Los Angeles, USA Jun 2021–Mar 2022

→ Collaborated with stakeholders across business units to identify and disambiguate requirements, as well as to validate that the developed solutions meet or surpass the requirements.

- → Designed, developed, and optimized data pipelines that operate at petabytes scale and deliver ad insights for a range of platforms, including digital and linear media.
- → Investigated machine learning models to optimize data pipeline performance, following extraction of novel insights through exploratory data analysis.
- → Mentored junior engineers in developing and optimizing data pipelines for delivering diverse analytics.

Samsung

Engineering and Commercialization, Media Platform

Noida, India Jul 2007-Aug 2011

- → Played an instrumental role in the commercialization of Java platform for mobile, set-top, and blu-ray product lines, coordinating development across teams in India and S. Korea. Teams' size: 10 members each.
- → Developed, ported, and optimized 2D Graphics module of Java Virtual Machine.
- → Mentored junior engineers in implementing graphics rendering and optimizing multithreaded execution.
- → Developed a web-based software component quality evaluation system.
- → Developed notebook apps focused on remote access and network management.

Internship

Centrum Wiskunde & Informatica

Amsterdam, Netherlands

Summer 2018

Research and Engineering, Interactive Systems Mentors: Dr. Pablo Cesar and Dr. Abdallah El Ali

- → Identified a research gap in supporting personal health tracker users in understanding their data.
- → Developed surveys to gather needs and evaluate visualizations for users' sensemaking of their sleep data.
- → Identified effective visualizations for sleep tracking through quantitative and qualitative data analyses.

Adobe Research San Jose, USA Summer 2017

Research and Engineering, Marketing Cloud

Mentor: Dr. Eunyee Koh

→ Identified a research problem in audience segmentation, engaging in discussions with marketing experts.

- → Developed interactive visualization of large-scale graph data to present audience overlaps across campaigns.
- → Established the system's efficacy through user studies followed by quantitative and qualitative data analyses.

Mountain View, USA Google

Engineering, Android Search Mentor: Amos Yoffe

Summer 2016

- → Developed module for presenting message results in Android In Apps search, clustered by topic and time.
- → Validated the new presentation method by creating a test dataset of messages and comparing search results.
- → Launched in September 2016, making the feature available worldwide.

Google Summer of Code

College Station, USA

Summer 2012

Engineering, Web Semantics

Host Organization: Interface Ecology Lab, Texas A&M University

- → Developed a RESTful service for meta-metadata structured web semantics represented in XML / JSON format.
- → Developed caching, database integration, logging, testing, and deployment modules.
- → Deployed the service in a production environment following a thorough investigation of available web servers.

Academic Research Projects

• Design Analytics [Human-Computer Interaction, Artificial Intelligence]

Spring 2017–Spring 2021

A human-centered AI investigation for assisting instructors in assessing a range of visual and conceptual characteristics present within student design work.

- → Engaged co-design discussions and workshops to understand instructors' situated practices and needs.
- → Developed an AI recognizer to measure students' use of space and scale in their free-form design work.
- → Deployed AI-based analytics via dashboards, as a technology probe, in situated course contexts.
- → Established efficacy through quantitative precision-recall measures and qualitative analysis of instructor interviews using a grounded theory approach.
- TweetBubble [Human-Computer Interaction]

Fall 2013-Fall 2016

A Chrome Extension for Twitter users to follow @usernames, #hashtags associations without tabs or windows.

→ Developed and deployed Chrome Extension, making it available worldwide.

- → Conducted studies during societal events such as the Academy Awards and Super Bowl.
- → Developed ideation metrics of exploratory browsing, including Fluency, Flexibility, and Novelty.
- → Established efficacy through a mixed methods evaluation, including quantitative ideation metrics and qualitative analysis of user experience data using grounded theory.
- Event Indicators [Natural Language Processing]

Spring 2016–Fall 2016

A weakly supervised approach for extracting and clustering event indicators from Twitter social media.

- → Cleaned up event relevant tweets, filtering duplicates arising from exact matches, substrings, punctuations, etc.
- → Applied bootstrapping to acquire a variety of civil unrest event cues, starting from a single strong indicator.
- BigSemantics [Software Engineering]

Fall 2012-Fall 2016

A software architecture for developing meta-metadata semantics powered dynamic exploratory browsing interfaces.

- → Developed new data models, extraction rules, and presentation semantics for social media.
- → Developed a RESTful service to facilitate semantics-driven application development across a range of contexts.
- EvolutionWorks [Human-Computer Interaction, Information Retrieval]

Fall 2011–Spring 2012

A free-form, zoomable space facilitating browsing, collection, and sensemaking of research papers interconnections.

- → Developed interface for presenting papers as cards within the free-form zoomable space.
- → Developed algorithm for determining representative terms present within a cluster when the user zooms out.
- → Established efficacy through user studies, comparing the interface with tabbed browsers.
- PhotoNav [Human-Computer Interaction]

Fall 2011–Spring 2012

A mixed reality investigation for assisting pedestrian navigation through the means of photographs.

- → Developed the NavCurator application for the specification of navigation paths over maps.
- → Evaluated handheld and head-mounted displays—through user studies—for assisting pedestrian navigation.

SKILLS

- Programming Languages: C, C++, Java, Python, Scala, R
- Web Programming: HTML, JavaScript, React, REST, Django, Node.js
- Big Data Technologies: HDFS, Spark, Kafka, Druid, Airflow
- Machine Learning Libraries: Scikit-learn, TensorFlow, Keras
- Visualization Libraries: D3.js, Three.js, Gephi
- Research Methods: Interviews, Surveys, Observations, Workshops, Grounded Theory, Hypothesis Testing

AWARDS & ACHIEVEMENTS

• Best Paper Nomination at ACM Document Engineering	2021
• Best Student Paper Nomination at ACM Document Engineering	2021
	2020-2021
• Student Travel Grant, College of Engineering, Texas A&M	2021
	2019-2020
	2018-2019
• Outstanding Reviewer Recognition for ACM CHI PLAY Full Papers	2019
• Academy for Future Faculty Certificate, Center for Teaching Excellence, Texas A&M	2018

•	Student Travel Grant, College of Engineering, Texas A&M	2017
•	Student Travel Grant, National Science Foundation	2017
•	Best Paper Honorable Mention at ACM Creativity & Cognition	2015
•	Student Travel Grant, College of Engineering, Texas A&M	2015
•	Extra Mile Award at Samsung	2010
•	Best Attitude Award at Samsung	2008
•	Six Sigma Green Belt at Samsung	2008

Refereed Conference Papers

- 1. Jain, A., Kerne, A., Lupfer, N., Britain, G., Perrine, A., Choe, Y., Keyser, J., and Huang, R. Recognizing Creative Visual Design: Multiscale Design Characteristics in Free-Form Web Curation Documents. In *Proceedings of the ACM Symposium on Document Engineering (DocEng) 2021*, 1-10 [33%]. Best Paper Nomination, Best Student Paper Nomination.
- 2. Kerne, A., Lupfer, N., Linder, R., Qu, Y., Valdez, A., Jain, A., Keith, K., Carrasco, M., Vanegas, J., Billingsley, A. Free-form Web Curation: Strategies for Creative Engagement with Prior Work. In *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Creativity & Cognition (C&C) 2017*, 380-392 [29%].
- Sharma, H. N., Toups, Z. O., Dolgov, I., Kerne, A., Jain, A. Evaluating Display Modalities using a Mixed Reality Game. In Proceedings of the ACM Annual Symposium on Computer-Human Interaction in Play (CHI PLAY) 2016, 65-77 [29%].
- 4. Jain, A., Lupfer, N., Qu, Y., Linder, R., Kerne, A., Smith, S. M. Evaluating TweetBubble with Ideation Metrics of Exploratory Browsing. In *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Creativity and Cognition (C&C) 2015*, 178-187 [28%]. Best Paper Honorable Mention Top 2%.
- Wilkins, J., Järvi, J., Jain, A., Kerne, A., Kejriwal, G., Gumudavelly, V. EvolutionWorks: Towards Improved Visualization of Citation Networks. In Proceedings of the IFIP Conference on Computer-Human Interaction (INTERACT) 2015, 213-230 [29.9%].
- Qu, Y., Kerne, A., Lupfer, N., Linder, R., Jain, A. Metadata Type System: Integrate Presentation, Data Models
 and Extraction to Enable Exploratory Browsing Interfaces. In Proceedings of the ACM Engineering Interactive
 Computing Systems (EICS) 2014, 107-116 [18%].
- 7. Fei, S., Webb, A. M., Kerne, A., Qu, Y., and **Jain, A.** Peripheral Array of Tangible NFC Tags: Positioning Portals for Embodied Trans-Surface Interaction. In *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Interactive Tabletops and Surfaces (ITS) 2013*, 33-36 [29%].
- 8. Jain, A. and Singh, S. Modified Programming Language Framework for IVRS Accessibility of Graphical User Interfaces. U-Media, pp.163-167, In *Proceedings of the IEEE Conference on Ubi-Media Computing (U-Media) 2011*, 163-167 [34%].

Refereed Workshops and Extended Abstracts

- 1. Britain, G., **Jain, A.**, Lupfer, N., Kerne, A., Perrine, A., Seo, J., Sungkajun, A. Design is (A)live: An Environment Integrating Ideation and Assessment, In *Extended Abstracts of the ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI Late-Breaking Work) 2020*, 1-8 [41.8%].
- 2. **Jain, A.** Measuring Creativity: Multi-Scale Visual and Conceptual Design Analysis. In *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Creativity & Cognition (C&C) 2017*, Graduate Student Symposium, 490-495.

- 3. Jain, A., Kasiviswanathan, G., and Huang, R. Towards Accurate Event Detection in Social Media: A Weakly Supervised Approach for Learning Implicit Event Indicators. In *Proceedings of the Computational Linguistics* (COLING) Workshop on Noisy User-Generated Text (WNUT) 2016, 70-77.
- 4. Sharma, H. N., Toups, Z. O., **Jain, A.**, Kerne, A. Designing to Split Attention in a Mixed Reality Game. In *Proceedings of the ACM Annual Symposium on Computer-Human Interaction in Play (CHI PLAY) 2015*, 691-696.
- 5. Fei, S., Kerne, A., **Jain, A.**, Webb, A. M., and Qu, Y. Positioning portals with peripheral NFC tags to embody trans-surface interaction. In *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Interactive Tabletops and Surfaces (ITS) 2013*, 317-320.

Presentations

• Recognizing Creative Visual Design: Multiscale Design Characteristics in Free-Form Web Curation Documents	Aug 2021
DocEng'21: Document Engineering	
• LiveMâché: Ideation on the Web	Sep 2020
Georgia Tech ME 6102: Designing Open Engineering Systems	
• Measuring Creativity: Multi-Scale Visual and Conceptual Design Analysis	Jun 2017
C&C'17: Creativity and Cognition (Graduate Student Symposium)	
• Towards Accurate Event Detection in Social Media	Dec 2016
COLING'17: Computational Linguistics	
• Evaluating TweetBubble with Ideation Metrics of Exploratory Browsing	Jun 2015
C&C'15: Creativity and Cognition	
• Programming Language Framework for IVRS Accessibility of Graphical User Interfaces	Jul 2011
UMEDIA'11: Ubi-Media Computing	

TEACHING

•	Instructor of Record, Dept. of Computer Science and Engineering, Texas A&M	Spring 2021
	CSCE 121 Introduction to Program Design and Concepts $(C++)$	
•	Teaching Assistant, Dept. of Computer Science and Engineering, Texas A&M	Spring 2015–Fall 2020

CSCE 655 Human-Centered Computing

CSCE 482 Senior Capstone Design

CSCE 444 Structures of Interactive Information

CSCE 420 Artificial Intelligence

CSCE 315 Programming Studio

CSCE 206 Structured Programming (C++)

CSCE 121 Introduction to Program Design and Concepts (C++)

MENTORING

• Gabriel Britain, Undergraduate Student in Computer Science, Texas A&M Fall 2019—Spring 2020 Research: Design analytics dashboards and their integration with a multiscale design environment.

• Hannah Fowler, Undergraduate Student in Computer Science, Texas A&M

Spring 2018-Fall 2018

Research: A grounded theory analysis of design instructors' teaching and assessment practices and needs.

• Aaron Perrine, Undergraduate Student in Computer Science, Texas A&M Spring 2018–Fall 2018

Research: Design analytics dashboards and their integration with a multiscale design environment.

• Alex Stacy, Undergraduate Student in Computer Science, Texas A&M

Fall 2016

Research: BigSemantics-based wrappers for extracting and presenting information from social media.

SERVICE

• Reviewer 2015–2021

ACM CHI 2022, 2021, 2020, 2019, 2017, 2016 ACM DIS 2022, 2021, 2020, 2019, 2018, 2016 ACM CSCW 2022, 2020, 2018 ACM C&C 2021, 2019, 2015 ACM CHI PLAY 2019, 2018, 2017 ACM ICMI 2021 CogSci 2021, 2019 EAI MobiHealth 2020 Psychonomic Bulletin 2019

• Associate Chair 2021

ACM Creativity & Cognition

• Judge, Student Research Week 2021

Texas A&M University

• Registration Chair 2019

ACM Creativity & Cognition

• Student Volunteer 2012

Design Computing and Cognition

References

Dr. Andruid Kerne

Professor

Department of Computer Science and Engineering Texas A&M University

⊠ andruid@ecologylab.net

Dr. Steven M. Smith

Professor

Department of Psychology Texas A&M University

⊠ stevesmith@tamu.edu

Dr. Ruihong Huang

Assistant Professor

Department of Computer Science and Engineering

Texas A&M University

⊠ huangrh@cse.tamu.edu

Dr. Jinsil Seo

Associate Professor

Department of Visualization

Texas A&M University

⊠ hwaryoung@tamu.edu